<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>XML Interfaces to the Internet of Things with XForms</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Steven</firstname>
          <surname>Pemberton</surname>
        </personname>
        <affiliation>
          <org>
            <orgname>CWI, Amsterdam</orgname>
          </org>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <abstract>
      <para> The internet of things is predicated on tiny, cheap, lower power computers being
        embedded in devices everywhere. However such tiny devices by definition have very little
        memory and computing power available to support user interfaces or extended servers, and so
        the user interface needs to be distributed over the network. </para>
      <para> This paper describes techniques using standard technologies based on XML for creating
        remote user-interfaces for the Internet of Things. </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Moore's Law is alive and well; to use the quote attributed to Mark Twain, the reports of
      its death have been greatly exaggerated. This year the 50th anniversary of Moore's Law was
      celebrated, which means since Moore's original paper was published, there have been 33⅓
      iterations of the law, which represents an improvement factor of ten thousand million since
      1965.</para>
    <para>As an excellent test point of Moore's Law's continuation, in February this year, almost
      exactly three years after the announcement of the first version, version 2 of the Raspberry Pi
      computer was announced. Moore's Law leads us to expect that every eighteen months you can get
      twice as many components per unit of surface area on an integrated circuit at the same price.
      (Note that, for instance, it doesn't say anything about expected clock speeds of computers).
      Since three years is exactly two cycles of Moore's Law, does the new Raspberry Pi deliver a
      four-fold improvement? Well, it is reportedly six times faster, has four times as many cores,
      four times as much memory, and twice as many USB ports as the original, all for the same
      price. Moore's Law has apparently done some pretty good work. </para>
    <para>Moore's Law has three parameters apart from time: price, size, and number of components.
      Hold any one of these constant, and the other two can vary accordingly. So apart from a
      Raspberry Pi that is the same price and size, but is better endowed, you can also reduce the
      price and size to get a less-powerful but nevertheless functional computer. This has been
      observable since the introduction of the first commercial computers in the 50's: with each
      order-of-magnitude decrease in price of computers, a new generation of computers has emerged,
      that gets used in a different sort of way. In the 50's you had mainframes that cost of the
      order of millions, in the 60's and 70's, minicomputers, of the order of 100,000; in the 70's
      and 80's, workstations, of the order of 10,000, and then starting in the early 80's the first
      home computers and laptops, in the order of thousands. Now we have netbooks and tablets of the
      order of hundreds, and an emerging class of computers, like the Arduino and the Raspberry Pi
      that cost of the order of tens (and since we're talking orders of magnitude, it doesn't matter
      if we're talking dollars, pounds, or euros, since they are all roughly of the same
      value).</para>

    <figure xml:id="sp-arduino">
      <title>Arduino</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/sp-arduino.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Recently the first computers of the order of one unit of currency have been appearing,
      such as the Arduino mini shown in <xref linkend="sp-arduino"/>.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>User Interfaces for Devices</title>
    <para>One of the unanticipated successes of HTML was in its adoption for controlling devices
      with embedded computers, such as home wifi routers. To make an adjustment to such a device,
      you direct your browser to the IP address the device is running from, and a small webserver on
      the device serves up webpages to you, that allow you to fill in values, and submit them to
      change the workings of the device.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sp-web-interface-router.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>However, the form-filling facilities of HTML are rather meager: you can fill in values,
      and submit them, but there is little checking possible on the client side, imposing a duty on
      the server to check values, and construct error pages that are sent back to the client asking
      for values to be corrected should they be wrong.</para>
    <para>However, the tiny computers that are and will be embedded and form part of the internet of
      things typically have memory in kilobytes, not megabytes, and certainly don't have the power
      to run a webserver that can serve and interpret webpages; therefore a different approach is
      called for.</para>
    <para>One way is for the devices to serve up just the data of the parameters, and accept new
      values for them, so that the values can be injected into a remote interface served from
      elsewhere.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>XForms</title>
    <para>One technology suitable for just such usage, XForms, is a standard developed at W3C <xref
        linkend="XForms"/>. XForms is a technology that was originally designed for improving the
      handling of forms on the web. It has two essential parts. The first part is the model, that
      specifies details of the data being collected, where it comes from, its structure, and
      constraints; it allows combining data from several sources, and submitting data to different
      places.</para>
    <para>The second part of XForms is the user interface, that displays values, and specifies
      controls for collection, modification, and submission of the data described, in a
      device-independent way.</para>
    <para>XForms has already been used for a number of years to control devices in this way at many
      petrol stations in the USA. Each device, storage tank, petrol pump, cash register, and so on,
      contains a simple server that delivers its data as XML instances. XForms interfaces are then
      used to read and combine these values, and update control values (for instance the price of
      fuel being displayed on pumps and charged at tills).</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Example: A Thermostat</title>
    <para>As an example of how it could be used, Nest, a well-known producer of internet
      thermostats, has published the data-model interface to its devices<footnote>
        <para>Nest API Reference - <link
            xl:href="https://developer.nest.com/documentation/api-reference"/></para>
      </footnote>. A simple interface to this could look like this:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<model>
  <instance id="thermostat"
            resource="http://thermostat.local/"/>
  <bind ref="ambient_temperature_c"
        type="decimal" readonly="true()"/>
  <bind ref="target_temperature_c"
        type="decimal"/>
  <bind ref="target_temperature_f" type="decimal"
   calculate="../target_temperature_c*9 div 5+32"/>
  <submission
    resource="http://thermostat.local/data"
    method="put" replace="instance"/>
</model> ]]></programlisting>
    <para>Here we see an instance that contains the data obtained from the thermostat, and three
      binds that assign properties to the data, in this case types, the property that the ambient
      temperature value is read-only, and a calculation that relates the values of the target
      temperature in Fahrenheit and Celsius, which ensures that whenever the Celsius value is
      changed, the Fahrenheit value automatically changes with it.</para>
    <para>The submission element specifies where the data is to be submitted, and what to do with
      the reply, in this case that it is data that replaces the instance values.</para>
    <para>A nice feature of this is that even if Nest changes the data structure returned by the
      thermostat, as long as the names of the elements used here remain the same, this interface
      will continue to work.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Display Values</title>
    <para>For a user interface for the thermostat, we need some extra local data values. In
      particular we want to offer the user the choice between Fahrenheit and Celsius in a single
      control. For this we need to add an extra instance to the model for the display values:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<instance id="display">
  <data xmlns="">
    <temperature/>
    <target>20</target>
    <scale>C</scale>
  </data>
</instance>
<bind ref="instance('display')/temperature"
  type="decimal"
  calculate="if(../scale='C', instance('thermostat')/ambient_temperature_c,        
                              instance('thermostat')/ambient_temperature_c * 9 div 5 + 32"/>
<bind ref="target" type="decimal"/>]]></programlisting>
    <para>Here we specify that the displayed temperature is related to the data from the device, but
      with a conversion if the user chooses for the Fahrenheit scale. Similarly, we have to add a
      relation back to the thermostat instance, so that the input required temperature is converted
      to Celsius if necessary:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bind
  ref="instance('thermostat')/target_temperature_c"
  calculate="if(instance('display')/scale='C',
                instance('display')/target,                    
               (instance('display')/target - 32) *
               5 div 9")/>]]></programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The User Interface</title>
    <para>XForms controls are specified in a device independent manner, that only describes what
      they are meant to achieve (for instance "pick one value from this list") and not how to do it
      (using radio buttons, using drop-downs etc.) This makes it easier to adapt the interface to
      different devices, screen sizes, etc., while still allowing the use of specific interfaces,
      such as radio buttons, via style sheets. For instance, to specify a control that allows the
      user to chose the temperature scale, we specify</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<select1 ref="instance('display')/scale"
         label="Scale">
  <item label="°C" value="C"/>
  <item label="°F" value="F"/> 
</select1>]]></programlisting>
    <para>This specification allows several different possible controls, for instance as a
      drop-down, or using radio buttons, depending on style-sheet options:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sp-cf1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sp-cf2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>


    <para>Similarly, the range control specifies an input for a number, that allows different
      styling options, such as nudge buttons, a slider, or a dial; a step attribute specifies the
      granularity of the changes:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<range ref="instance('display')/target" step="0.5"
        start="0" end="30"/>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Of course, these start and end values are in Celsius, and we want to specify the limits in
      terms of the scale used. However, any attribute can have a calculated value, using attribute
      value templates:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<range ref="instance('display')/target" step="0.5" 
  start="{instance('display')/start}"
  end="{instance('display')/end}"/>]]></programlisting>

    <para>and add these values to the display instance:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<instance id="display">
  <data xmlns="">
    <temperature/>
    <target>20</target>
    <start/>
    <end/>
    <scale>C</scale>
  </data>
</instance>
<bind ref="instance('display')/start"
      calculate="if(../scale='C', 0, 32"/>
<bind ref="instance('display')/end"
      calculate="if(../scale='C', 30, 90"/>]]></programlisting>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Submitting Data</title>
    <para>Normally in a form-based interface, there is an explicit [submit] button or similar that
      indicates you are ready with the data and want to submit it to be used.</para>
    <para>For instance, in XForms, you would typically have details about where the data is to be
      submitted, in the form of a submission element in the model, as above:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<submission resource="http://thermostat.local/data"
            method="put" replace="instance"/>]]></programlisting>
    <para>This specifies the URL that the data is to be submitted to, the method to be used (PUT in
      this case), and what to do with the result. In the case of the thermostat, the state of the
      internal values are returned again, and these are just used to overwrite the values in the
      instance.</para>
    <para>Then in the user interface, there would be a submit control, that initiates the
      submission, normally displayed as a clickable button:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<submit label="Submit"/>]]></programlisting>
    <para>However, typically in a direct-manipulation style interface such as a thermometer, there
      is no moment that you explicitly submit the data: it just happens. To effect this in XForms,
      the submission has to be done automatically. This can be done by using the standard event
      mechanism inherited in XForms from DOM-based systems <xref linkend="DOM-Events"/>, and using
      XML Events <xref linkend="XML-Events"/> to listen for events, and react to them.</para>
    <para>One of the events that XForms generates is the xforms-value-changed event, which is
      generated everytime a value is changed in an instance by a control. There are several ways of
      specifying this, but the most direct is to include, as a child of the control, an action that
      responds to the event:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<range ref="instance('display')/target" step="0.5" 
       start="{instance('display')/start}"
       end="{instance('display')/end}">
  <action ev:event="xforms-value-changed">
    <send/>
  </action>
</range>]]></programlisting>
    <para>This says that whenever the <code>&lt;range&gt;</code> control receives the
      xforms-value-changed event because the bound value has been changed, then the
        <code>&lt;send/&gt;</code> action is initiated, which causes the submission to do its work.
      When an <code>&lt;action&gt;</code> element only has one child like this, then it can be
      contracted:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<range ref="instance('display')/target" step="0.5" 
       start="{instance('display')/start}"
       end="{instance('display')/end}">
  <send ev:event="xforms-value-changed"/>
</range>]]></programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Polling</title>
    <para>As a result of submitting data as shown above, the thermostat returns the current values
      in its internal state, including the currently measured temperature, which then gets
      displayed.</para>
    <para>Of course, you want to continue to display the current temperature, even if the user
      hasn't changed anything via the interface. To achieve this, the data has to be periodically
      polled. This can be done also using the event mechanism, by listening for timing events: at
      start up you initiate a timer, and then listen for the event to go off. When it goes off, you
      respond, and then re-initiate the timer:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<action ev:event="my-timer">
  <send/>
  <dispatch name="my-timer" delay="20000"
            targetid="parent"/>
</action>]]></programlisting>
    <para>This <code>&lt;action/&gt;</code> element can go anywhere, as long as its parent element
      has id 'parent' (as named in this case) . The delay is specified in milliseconds, so in this
      case, every 20 seconds the thermostat is polled for its current values.</para>
    <para>The only other thing that has to be done is to start off the initial timer, by listening
      for the xforms-ready event, which is dispatched when an XForm starts up:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<action ev:event="xforms-ready">
  <dispatch name="my-timer" delay="20000"
            targetid="parent"/>
</action>]]></programlisting>
    <para>As in the earlier case, this can be shortened:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dispatch ev:event="xforms-ready" name="my-timer"
          delay="20000" targetid="parent"/>]]></programlisting>
    <para>Since the xforms-ready event is dispatched to the <code>&lt;model&gt;</code> element, this
        <code>&lt;dispatch/&gt;</code> element should be a direct child of it, and since it doesn't
      matter where the other action is placed, it can also be placed there:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<model id="model">
  ...
  <dispatch ev:event="xforms-ready" name="my-timer"
            delay="20000" targetid="model"/>
  <action ev:event="my-timer">
    <send/>
    <dispatch name="my-timer" delay="20000"
              targetid="model"/>
  </action>   
</model>]]></programlisting>
    <para>Of course, the delay value doesn't have to be hard-wired like this, but can also be stored
      in an instance, and accessed from there:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<model id="model">
  ...
  <dispatch ev:event="xforms-ready" name="my-timer"
  delay="{instance('display')/poll-interval}"
  targetid="model"/>
  <action ev:event="my-timer">
    <send/>
    <dispatch name="my-timer"
      delay="{instance('display')/poll-interval}"
      targetid="model"/>
  </action>   
</model>]]></programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Repetition</title>
    <para>In many applications, there can be a variable number of values for a particular field; for
      instance in a router, there can be several rules for firewall exceptions. Traditionally an
      interface is used that offers several blank entries to be filled in. However XForms offers a
      dynamic control that grows and shrinks with the number of entries, and allows entries to be
      added and deleted:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<repeat ref="firewall/rules" label="Exceptions">
  <output ref="./port" label="Port"/>
  <output ref="./url" label="URL" />
</repeat>]]></programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Multilingual Interfaces</title>
    <para>Every XForms control has a label. Of course, it is good to be able to offer an interface
      in the language of the user. Attribute value templates make this almost trivially easy: you
      create an instance to hold the messages and labels:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<instance id="label"
  resource="http://example.com/labels-en.xml" />]]></programlisting>
    <para>which can have a structure like:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<labels lang="en">
  <submit>Submit</submit>
  <help>Help</help>
  <scale>Scale</scale>
  ...
</label>]]></programlisting>
    <para>and then reference these in the controls:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<select1 ref="instance('display')/scale"
         label="{instance('label')/scale}"> ...]]></programlisting>
    <para>Changing the language is then a simple case of having a control that selects the language
      wanted:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<select1 ref="instance('lang')/language"
         label="{instance('label')/language}"> ...]]></programlisting>
    <para>and when an xforms-value-changed happens on this control, the value chosen can be
      submitted, and the labels instance replaced with the returned instance.</para>
    <para>These also has the advantage that lables are not hard-wired in the application, and can be
      updated on the fly. And of course the languages available can also be provided by an external
      instance, so that new languages can be added on the fly.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Experience</title>
    <para>XForms has been used in many projects connecting to devices, including some very large
      projects of many person-years. Experience has repeatedly shown that the time needed to
      implement such projects is about one tenth of equivalent projects done using traditional
      programming methods. This advantage can largely be ascribed to the declarative nature of
      XForms, so that much administrative code that is normally needed in programs is not needed in
      XForms, since the system ensures that invariants are kept up to date.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifications and implementations</title>
    <para>The current official version of XForms is XForms 1.1 <xref linkend="XForms11"/>, though
      XForms 2.0 is in preparation and close to completion <xref linkend="XForms20"/>. There are
      several implementations available, that work both server-side and client-side, both commercial
      and open-source. There is a tutorial <xref linkend="TUT"/> and a quick reference <xref
        linkend="QR"/> available.</para>
  </section>

  <bibliography>

    <title>References</title>

    <biblioentry xml:id="XForms">
      <abbrev>1</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Micah</firstname>
            <surname>Dubinko</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Leigh</firstname>
            <surname>Klotz</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Roland</firstname>
            <surname>Merrick</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>T. V.</firstname>
            <surname>Raman</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>

      </authorgroup>
      <title>XForms 1.0</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>14 October 2003</date>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/REC-xforms-20031014/</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="DOM-Events">
      <abbrev>2</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Tom</firstname>
            <surname>Pixley</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>Document Object Model (DOM) Level 2 Events Specification</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>13 November, 2000</date>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/DOM-Level-2-Events/</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="XML-Events">
      <abbrev>3</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Shane</firstname>
            <surname>McCarron</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Steven</firstname>
            <surname>Pemberton</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>T. V.</firstname>
            <surname>Raman</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>XML Events</title>
      <subtitle>An Events Syntax for XML</subtitle>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>14 October 2003</date>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/REC-xml-events-20031014/</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="XForms11">
      <abbrev>4</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>John</firstname>
            <surname>Boyer</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>XForms 1.1</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>20 October 2009</date>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/xforms/</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="XForms20">
      <abbrev>5</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>John</firstname>
            <surname>Boyer</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Erik</firstname>
            <surname>Bruchez</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Leigh</firstname>
            <surname>Klotz</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Steven</firstname>
            <surname>Pemberton</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Nick</firstname>
            <surname>Van den Bleeken</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>XForms 2.0</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/Forms/wiki/XForms_2.0</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="TUT">
      <abbrev>6</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Steven</firstname>
            <surname>Pemberton</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>XForms for HTML Authors</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>27 August 2010</date>
      <biblioid class="uri"
        >http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/Forms/2010/xforms11-for-html-authors/</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="QR">
      <abbrev>7</abbrev>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>
            <firstname>Steven</firstname>
            <surname>Pemberton</surname>
          </personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <title>XForms 1.1 Quick Reference</title>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <date>29 November 2010</date>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/Forms/2010/xforms11-qr.html</biblioid>
    </biblioentry>

  </bibliography>

</article>
