<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/dbsvg.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="paper-4" xml:lang="en-GB" version="5.0">
  <info xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Dynamic Translation of Modular XML Documentation Using Linked Data</title>
    <titleabbrev>XML London 2016</titleabbrev>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Simon</firstname>
        <surname>Dew</surname>
      </personname>
      <email>simonjabadaw@gmail.com</email>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>STANLEY Black and Decker Innovations Limited</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <!-- <pubdate>5 May 2016</pubdate> -->
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>XML</keyword>
      <keyword>Translation</keyword>
      <keyword>DocBook</keyword>
      <keyword>SVG</keyword>
      <keyword>ITS</keyword>
      <keyword>XLIFF</keyword>
      <keyword>Linked Data</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <para>STANLEY Black and Decker Innovations had a requirement to produce and
      maintain DocBook-based documentation, which is translated into up to 10 languages.
      Documents are built by transclusion from several source files, some of which may be
      stored remotely. Each document may contain SVG illustrations which also needed
      translation.</para>
      <para>We selected XLIFF as a translation file format. To keep maintenance effort to
      a minimum, we needed tools that enabled dynamic translations, i.e. translations
      made at publication time without skeleton files. We also needed tools that could
      find the correct translations for each translatable element after all the source
      files (including remote source files) had been transcluded into a single
      document.</para>
      <para>This article describes the solutions we developed. These included markup
      (mostly ITS 2.0) in the source documentation, linked data (using RDF/XML) to
      identify the translation resources, and a set of XSLT stylesheets to handle the
      transformations.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-4_intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>XML-based documentation often requires translation and localisation. The QRT
    team at STANLEY Black and Decker Innovations had a requirement to produce and
    maintain modular documentation in up to 10 languages. Any translated document might
    be published in up to 4 different brandings, for a number of different varieties of a
    product, in several different output formats, e.g. PDF, CHM, web help; and each
    document might contain illustrations which also needed translation. This article
    describes the solutions we developed to minimise the effort and cost required to do
    this.</para>
  </section>
  <section xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-4_background">
    <title>Background</title>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_background_format">
      <title>Translation File Format</title>
      <para>We required an open source format to store translations. We considered two
      main standards: the <firstterm>GNU gettext</firstterm> standard and the
      <firstterm>XLIFF</firstterm> file format.</para>
      <para>The GNU gettext standard is an internationalisation and localisation system,
      released by the GNU project and based on earlier work by Sun Micrososystems
      <biblioref linkend="paper-4_gettext"/>. It uses text files known as Portable Objects to
      hold translation strings. Commonly used for user interfaces in UNIX-like operating
      systems.</para>
      <para>XLIFF (XML Localisation Interchange File Format) is a data exchange
      standard for localisation, originally designed for passing localisation data
      between translation tools <biblioref linkend="paper-4_xliff"/>. It’s an XML-based file
      format, standardised by OASIS (the Organization for the Advancement of Structured
      Information Standards) in 2002.</para>
      <para>We chose the XLIFF file format because:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Commercial translation houses can use XLIFF comfortably with their
          proprietary translation tools;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>XLIFF being XML-based can be transformed using XSLT <biblioref linkend="paper-4_xslt10"/>, and it made sense to use this with our DocBook XML
          documentation <biblioref linkend="paper-4_docbook"/> and SVG images <biblioref linkend="paper-4_svg"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_background_static">
      <title>Traditional XLIFF Workflow</title>
      <para>The traditional XLIFF workflow demands that the source document is converted
      into a <firstterm>skeleton file</firstterm> which contains the structure of the
      document, and an XLIFF file which contains the translation units themselves, as
      shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_static_translate"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_static_translate">
        <title>Translation with skeleton file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_static_translate.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <blockquote>
        <attribution><biblioref linkend="paper-4_ibm"/></attribution>
        <para>Filters store the non-translatable portions in special files called
        skeletons.</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>The XLIFF file is sent to the translators. After translation, the translated
      XLIFF files are combined with the skeleton file to create translated documents in
      each of the target languages, as shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_static_merge"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_static_merge">
        <title>Merge with skeleton file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_static_merge.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The translated documents are then processed to create the desired
      output formats, as shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_static_publish"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_static_publish">
        <title>Publishing translated documents</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_static_publish.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <blockquote>
        <attribution><biblioref linkend="paper-4_ibm"/></attribution>
        <para>The translated XLIFF must now be merged with the skeleton file to produce a
        translated document in the desired output format.</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>This means, however, that the skeleton file and the translated
      documents become resources which must themselves be maintained:</para>
      <blockquote>
        <attribution><biblioref linkend="paper-4_tektronix"/></attribution>
        <para>Translated file is checked into XML repository</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>Maintaining skeleton files and a large number of translated files can become
      a problem, especially when authors have to produce several different versions of
      the documentation, e.g. for different brandings or product variants.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_background_dynamic">
      <title>Dynamic Translations</title>
      <para>One solution to the problem of maintenance of translated documentation is to
      use <firstterm>dynamic translations</firstterm>. The translation strings are
      extracted from the source file, but no skeleton file is produced, as shown in
      <xref linkend="paper-4_dynamic_translate"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_dynamic_translate">
        <title>Translation without skeleton file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_dynamic_translate.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>At publication time, the build tool takes the structure of the source
      document and replaces the source text with the corresponding translated text,
      including any inline markup, as shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_dynamic_publish"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_dynamic_publish">
        <title>Publishing translated documents dynamically</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_dynamic_publish.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The advantage of fully dynamic translation is that elements can be moved
      around or deleted in the source document and these structural changes are reflected
      automatically in the translated publications, without the need to regenerate the
      skeleton file or update intermediate translated source files.</para>
      <para>Dynamic translation is used with some GNU gettext workflows. For example,
      authors who write documentation in the Mallard XML format <biblioref linkend="paper-4_mallard"/> can use this approach to publish documentation to yelp, the
      GNOME help viewer <biblioref linkend="paper-4_yelp"/>. Authors can place translated PO
      files into a specific subdirectory and add instructions to a configuration file so
      the build process can translate the document into that language:</para>
      <blockquote>
        <attribution><biblioref linkend="paper-4_yelp"/></attribution>
        <para>This integrates the British English language translation with the yelp.m4
        build process, so that the translations from the PO file are used to create
        translated Mallard pages during the make process. As with the basic integration,
        the translated pages are validated during make check and installed in the install
        directory during make install.</para>
      </blockquote>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_background_problem">
      <title>Problem</title>
      <para>However, we faced two problems before we could adopt this approach:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>We weren’t aware of any solution that would enable dynamic translation
          using XLIFF files.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A further problem arises with modular documentation, i.e. documents that
          are built at publication time from several source files, all transcluded into
          the main assembly document. Some of these source files may be stored remotely.
          The publication process thus needs to know where to find the correct
          translation for every translatable element in the main document after all the
          document source files have been transcluded into a single document. See
          <xref linkend="paper-4_modular_problem"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_modular_problem">
        <title>Problem with translating modular documentation</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_modular_problem.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-4_design">
    <title>Design</title>
    <para>We designed a solution based around linked data to identify the translation
    files for each document, document part or image; markup in the source documentation
    to identify the correct translation for each translatable element; and a set of tools
    to handle the translation process. See <xref linkend="paper-4_modular_solution"/>.</para>
    <figure xml:id="paper-4_modular_solution" pgwide="1">
      <title>Dynamic translation using linked data</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/2016_modular_solution.svg" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_links">
      <title>Design: Linked Data</title>
      <para>Each source document can use linked data to identify the XLIFF files that
      contain translations of the elements within the document. We wanted linked data to
      reuse established vocabularies wherever possible.</para>
      <para>If necessary, specific parts of a document (e.g. document chunks which have
      been transcluded from a remote location) can use linked data to identify the
      XLIFF files that contain translations of the elements within that part.</para>
      <para>Linked translation data takes the form of RDF/XML statement(s) <biblioref linkend="paper-4_rdfxml"/>. We chose RDF/XML because of the flexibility that the markup
      offers, and in the hope that we may find further ways to analyse our translations
      using linked data tools in future, e.g. to analyse translation coverage.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_markup">
      <title>Design: Markup</title>
      <para>Each translatable element must contains markup that identifies the
      corresponding translation unit in the XLIFF file.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_tools">
      <title>Design: Tools</title>
      <para>Translation will take place as part of the document build process, after
      transcluding the document modules into a single document, and before transforming
      the document into its publication format. The solution must therefore include an
      automatic translation tool which can be used as part of the document publication
      build process.</para>
      <para>For each translatable element in the document, the automatic translation tool
      must find the correct XLIFF file for the correct language, and replace the inline
      content of the element with the translated content from the XLIFF file.</para>
      <para>The solution must include tools to prepare the source documentation for
      translation, i.e. by adding translation markup automatically; and to extract the
      translatable strings to an XLIFF file so that it can be sent to translators.</para>
      <para>The solution must also include tools for the management of XLIFF files: for
      example, comparing the source file to the translation file when the source file has
      changed; merging completed translations into the existing translation files; and
      purging duplicate translation units from existing translation files.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_prior">
      <title>Related Work</title>
      <para>As stated previously, we were aware of gettext for handling dynamic
      translations. However, gettext is not aimed at XLIFF files, and does not address
      the issue of translating modular documentation.</para>
      <para>We were also aware of the ITS Tool <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://itstool.org"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote> package for maintaining translation files. This package provided useful
      inspiration, particularly the use of ITS (Internationalisation Tag Set) rules files
      to identify translatable elements <biblioref linkend="paper-4_its"/>. However, this package
      is also aimed at gettext Portable Objects rather than XLIFF files, and does not
      address the issue of translating modular documentation.</para>
      <para>The Okapi Framework <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://okapi.opentag.com"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote> is a suite of tools for managing XLIFF files, particularly useful for
      extracting XLIFF translatable units from a wide variety of file formats. It does
      not handle dynamic translation, or provide any solution to the issue of translating
      modular documentation.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_mapping">
      <title>Design Decision: Mapping Elements to Translation Units</title>
      <para>When converting from the source documentation to XLIFF, the preparation tools
      need to be able to determine what a translatable element is, and how the
      translatable elements map to XLIFF translation units.</para>
      <para>One approach would be to convert all elements containing text nodes into
      translation units. However this might lead to highly segmented text, which would
      create difficulties for translators.</para>
      <para>To aid translators, and to keep the implementation simple, we decided to
      define a reasonable set of elements for each supported file type as
      <quote>block</quote> elements. Each block element maps to a single translation
      unit. So for example, in DocBook XML, a <tag class="element">para</tag> or a <tag class="element">title</tag> tag would be a block element. Child elements of block
      element are <quote>inline</quote> elements, contained within the XLIFF translation
      unit.</para>
      <para>The ITS 2.0 standard provides the Elements Within Text data category, which
      can be used to determine which elements in a file are block elements and which are
      inline. We decided to define a standard ITS rules file for the file formats we use.
      The XLIFF preparation tools must use this ITS rules file to map the elements in the
      source document to translation units in an XLIFF file. The XLIFF preparation tools
      must be able to use different ITS rules files if necessary.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_inline">
      <title>Design Decision: Inline Markup</title>
      <para>Elements from foreign namespaces are not permitted within translated text
      in an XLIFF file. XLIFF supports two strategies for marking up inline elements.
      These may be called <quote>raw</quote> (escaped) markup and <quote>cooked</quote>
      (transformed) markup.</para>
      <para>With raw markup, inline XML elements in the source document are marked up in
      the XLIFF file as escaped text. Escaped start and end tags can be surrounded by
      XLIFF <tag class="element">bpt</tag> and <tag class="element">ept</tag> tags;
      escaped standalone tags can be surrounded by XLIFF <tag class="element">ph</tag>
      tags. The escaped markup has to be unescaped when inserting text into the
      translated document.</para>
      <para>With cooked markup, inline XML elements in the source document are
      transformed into XLIFF elements. Inline elements with content can be transformed
      into XLIFF <tag class="element">g</tag> elements; inline elements with no content
      can be transformed into XLIFF <tag class="element">x</tag> elements. Since we want
      to do without a skeleton file, the XLIFF maintenance tools would have to store the
      <tag class="element">g</tag> and <tag class="element">x</tag> elements with enough
      information to be able to transform them losslessly back into the original inline
      elements, with the original namespace, local name and attributes. We decided that
      when using cooked markup, we would use the <tag class="attribute">ctype</tag>
      attribute to record the original namespace and local name of inline elements. XLIFF
      permits attributes from foreign namespaces.</para>
      <para>We prefer using raw inline tags in our XLIFF files in-house. When using an
      XLIFF-capable editor such as Virtaal <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://virtaal.translatehouse.org"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote>, we found it useful to see the full content of any inline markup. We
      decided to use raw (escaped) inline markup as the primary format for XLIFF files.
      However our translation houses preferred to work with cooked (transformed) inline
      markup. We decided that our maintenance tools must therefore be able to round-trip
      XLIFF files, i.e. convert an XLIFF file from one format to the other, preserving
      the structure of the inline elements.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_design_nesting">
      <title>Design Decision: Nested Block Elements</title>
      <para>Our primary documentation format, DocBook XML, allows nested block elements.
      For example, a DocBook <tag class="element">para</tag> element can contain a <tag class="element">footnote</tag> element, which in turn can contain another <tag class="element">para</tag> element. This could be handled by XLIFF, e.g. by
      representing the inner block element as an inline element, and using the <tag class="attribute">xid</tag> attribute to refer to another translation unit. We
      decided however, for the sake of simplicity, not to implement this at first. We
      decided to enforce a local writing convention that authors could not nest <tag class="element">para</tag> elements. If necessary, we would use a <tag class="element">simpara</tag> element within a <tag class="element">para</tag>
      element. The XLIFF preparation tool must regard <tag class="element">simpara</tag>
      as an inline element.</para>
      <para>Similarly, we decided to enforce a local writing convention that no
      attributes could contain translatable text.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-4_solution">
    <title>Solution</title>
    <para>We implemented this design as part of a broader document localisation and
    publication project, which was known within STANLEY Black and Decker Innovations as
    <firstterm>PACBook</firstterm>.</para>
    <para>PACBook is released under version 3.0 of the GNU Lesser General Public License
    <biblioref linkend="paper-4_lgpl"/>. It is available from the PACBook repository on GitHub at
    <link xl:href="https://github.com/STANLEYSecurity/PACBook"/>.</para>
    <para>The parts of PACBook which implement dynamic translation for XML documents
    using linked data are described here. Full documentation for the entire project is
    available from the PACBook repository on GitHub.</para>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_rdf">
      <title>Implementation: Linked Data</title>
      <para>To be able to translate an XML document using this solution, authors must add
      a <firstterm>translation statement</firstterm> to the metadata section of the XML
      document. So, for a DocBook 5.0 document, you would add it to the <tag class="element">info</tag> element at the start of the document. For an SVG image,
      you would add it to the <tag class="element">metadata</tag> element at the start of
      the image.</para>
      <para>We use terms from the Bibliographic Ontology (BIBO) to identify the document,
      document part or image that needs translation. <biblioref linkend="paper-4_bibo"/></para>
      <para>We use terms from the VIVO Integrated Semantic Framework vocabulary to
      specify the location of the XLIFF files which contain the translations for this
      document, document part or image. <biblioref linkend="paper-4_vivo"/></para>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_rdf_document">
        <title>Linked Data for a Document</title>
        <para>A typical translation statement for a DocBook XML document is shown in
        <xref linkend="paper-4_eg_solution_rdf"/>.</para>
        <example xml:id="paper-4_eg_solution_rdf">
          <title>Translation statement for a DocBook document</title>
          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
         xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/"
         xmlns:vivo="http://vivoweb.org/ontology/core#"
  &lt;bibo:Document rdf:about=""&gt;
    &lt;vivo:hasTranslation xml:base="http://DBK/Topics/512_Series/xlate/"&gt;
      &lt;rdf:Alt&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="de" rdf:resource="ac_de.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="es" rdf:resource="ac_es.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="fr" rdf:resource="ac_fr.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="nb" rdf:resource="ac_nb.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="nl" rdf:resource="ac_nl.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="sv" rdf:resource="ac_sv.xliff"/&gt;
        &lt;rdf:li xml:lang="zh" rdf:resource="ac_zh.xliff"/&gt;
      &lt;/rdf:Alt&gt;
    &lt;/vivo:hasTranslation&gt;
    &lt;!-- Other RDF properties ... --&gt;
  &lt;/bibo:Document&gt;
&lt;/rdf:RDF&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <tag class="element">bibo:Document</tag> property declares that
            this file is a document and that it is the subject of this statement.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <tag class="element">vivo:hasTranslation</tag> property declares
            that this document has translations associated with it. The optional <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> attribute can be used to indicate where all
            the translations are.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The translation resources are indicated by the <tag class="element">rdf:li</tag> elements. For each translation, the <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute represents the language; the <tag class="attribute">rdf:resource</tag> attribute shows the URI of the XLIFF
            file which contains the translation in that language. The <tag class="attribute">rdf:resource</tag> attribute may contain an absolute or
            relative URI; if relative, it is combined with the <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> attribute of the <tag class="element">vivo:hasTranslation</tag> property to define the full
            URI.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Note that you need to declare the <tag class="namespace">rdf</tag>,
            <tag class="namespace">bibo</tag> and <tag class="namespace">vivo</tag>
            namespaces. The namespace URIs are shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_eg_solution_rdf"/>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The DocBook 5.0 schema allows foreign namespaces within the <tag class="element">info</tag> element, so there is no need to extend the DocBook 5.0
        schema to add the translation statement.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_rdf_img">
        <title>Linked Data for an Image</title>
        <para>You would use <tag class="element">bibo:Image</tag> instead of <tag class="element">bibo:Document</tag> in a translation statement that applies to an
        SVG file.</para>
        <para>SVG files allow elements in foreign namespaces anywhere, so similarly there
        is no need to extend the SVG schema to add the translation statement.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_rdf_part">
        <title>Linked Data for Document Parts</title>
        <para>You can also specify a translation statement for part of a file. The
        easiest way to do this is to add it to the metadata section for that part. So, in
        a DocBook file, you would add a translation statement that only applies to a
        particular chapter to the <tag class="element">info</tag> element at the start of
        the chapter. This would override any translation statement at the start of the
        book. If the chapter is transcluded from a different location, its translation
        statement can be transcluded along with it.</para>
        <para>You would use <tag class="element">bibo:DocumentPart</tag> instead of <tag class="element">bibo:Document</tag> in a translation statement that only applies
        to part of a document.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_markup">
      <title>Implementation: Markup</title>
      <para>In the source documents, authors mark up translatable elements using an
      attribute from the XLIFF namespace, namely <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag>. The
      <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag> attribute corresponds to the ID of a single,
      unique translation unit in an XLIFF file. There’s no requirement that the value of
      <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag> should be unique in the source document.</para>
      <para>We also allow all the local attributes from the ITS namespace in the source
      documents. ITS local attributes are used as specified by the ITS 2.0
      recommendation, e.g. to mark up localisation notes and terminology, or to indicate
      whether a translatable element should be translated.</para>
      <note>
        <para>Why do we use <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag>? The ITS 2.0
        recommendation stipulates that:</para>
        <blockquote>
          <attribution><biblioref linkend="paper-4_its"/></attribution>
          <para>The recommended way to specify a unique identifier is to use <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> or <tag class="attribute">id</tag> in
          HTML.</para>
        </blockquote>
        <para>However, after transclusion, the same translatable element may appear more
        than once in the document. Obviously two elements cannot have the same <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag>.</para>
        <para>Further, if the <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> of an element were
        changed or fixed up after transclusion, it would be more difficult to use the
        <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> to find the correct translation unit for that
        element.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Typical markup of translatable elements in a DocBook XML document is shown in
      <xref linkend="paper-4_eg_solution_markup"/>.</para>
      <example xml:id="paper-4_eg_solution_markup">
        <title>Markup of translatable elements</title>
        <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;important xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
  xmlns:xlf="urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:document:1.2"
  version="5.0-variant PACBook"
  its:version="2.0"&gt;
  &lt;title its:translate="no"/&gt;
  &lt;itemizedlist&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para xlf:id="u00182"&gt;Risk of explosion if
      battery is replaced by an incorrect type.
      Use only 12V sealed lead acid battery.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
    &lt;listitem&gt;
      &lt;para xlf:id="u00183"&gt;Dispose of used
      batteries in accordance with local and
      national regulations.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/listitem&gt;
  &lt;/itemizedlist&gt;
&lt;/important&gt;
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>Note that you need to declare the <tag class="namespace">its</tag> and <tag class="namespace">xliff</tag> namespaces. The namespace URIs are shown in <xref linkend="paper-4_eg_solution_markup"/>.</para>
      <para>Note also that documents which use the ITS 2.0 local attributes must have an
      <tag class="attribute">its:version</tag> attribute set to <tag class="attvalue">2.0</tag>.</para>
      <para>We’ve created a custom extension to the DocBook 5.0 schema which adds these
      attributes. The custom extension is implemented in a Relax NG schema called
      <filename>pacbook.rng</filename> <biblioref linkend="paper-4_rng"/>. This is available at
      the PACBook repository on GitHub. Documents using this extended schema must have a
      <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute set to <tag class="attvalue">5.0-variant PACBook</tag>.</para>
      <para>SVG files allow attributes in different namespaces, so there is no need to
      create a custom schema to allow these attributes in SVG files.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_xslt">
      <title>Implementation: Tools</title>
      <para>We implemented the translation tools using XSLT stylesheets. These XSLT
      stylesheets are available from the PACBook repository on GitHub. The stylesheets
      can be divided into three groups:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Stylesheets which enable authors to prepare a document for
          translation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Stylesheets which translate the source document as part of the build
          process.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Stylesheets for the management of XLIFF files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>A full description of each XSLT stylesheet is beyond the scope of this
      article. A brief overview of each stylesheet is given here. Full documentation on
      each of them can be found in the PACBook repository on GitHub.</para>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_xslt_prepare">
        <title>Preparation Stylesheets</title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateMarkup.xsl</title>
              <para>Adds <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag> attributes to a file. This
              stylesheet uses an ITS rules file to identify the translatable elements.
              The location of the ITS rules file is specified by stylesheet parameter.
              Each <tag class="attribute">xlf:id</tag> attribute is given a unique
              consecutive numerical value. The latest numerical value is stored in an XML
              file whose location is also specified by stylesheet parameter.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateExtract.xsl</title>
              <para>Extracts all translatable elements to an XLIFF file. The XLIFF file
              can then be sent to translators.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateDiff.xsl</title>
              <para>Compares a source document to existing XLIFF file and creates a new
              XLIFF file containing only the new and changed translation units. This is
              useful when a source document has changed.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateMerge.xsl</title>
              <para>Merges complete translations from a translated XLIFF file into an
              existing XLIFF file. This is useful when a XLIFF file comes back from the
              translators.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_xslt_build">
        <title>Build Stylesheets</title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateConvert.xsl</title>
              <para>Translates the document to a single language, specified by stylesheet
              parameter. This stylesheet uses the linked translation data in the document
              to work out which XLIFF file to use when translating each element.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateCombine.xsl</title>
              <para>Creates inline multilingual translations. Similar to
              <filename>XlateConvert.xsl</filename>; however, this stylesheet translates
              the document to each of the languages specified by the stylesheet parameter
              and combines each translation inline.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XlateID.xsl</title>
              <para>Fixes up <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attributes in
              multilingual translations. It simply adds the current language code to the
              end of all <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> and link attributes. This is
              useful if you use a two-step build process to create multilingual
              translations, first translating the source document into several languages
              and then combining the translations into a larger document.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_xslt_management">
        <title>XLIFF Management Stylesheets</title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XliffDupe.xsl</title>
              <para>Removes duplicate translation units from an XLIFF file. Duplicate
              translation units can occur in an XLIFF file that has been extracted from a
              source document with repeated identical translatable elements, e.g.
              translatable elements that have been transcluded into more than one
              location. This stylesheet performs a deterministic deduplication; if more
              than one translation unit has the same ID, the first is kept and the rest
              are discarded.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XliffPurge.xsl</title>
              <para>Removes completed translation units from an XLIFF file. This is
              useful when an XLIFF file has been partially translated, e.g. by an
              in-house translation memory, and you want to remove the translated strings
              before sending the XLIFF file for translation.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XliffRaw.xsl</title>
              <para>Escapes inline markup in an XLIFF file — preferred by some
              translation houses.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XliffTemp.xsl + XliffTag.xsl</title>
              <para>Unescapes inline markup in an XLIFF file — if required.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Xliff2CSV.xsl</title>
              <para>Exports an XLIFF file to CSV.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>XL2Xliff.xsl</title>
              <para>Imports from a Microsoft Excel 2003 XML file to XLIFF.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_solution_build">
      <title>Solution: Build Process</title>
      <para>We use Apache Ant <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://ant.apache.org"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote> build scripts to automate the transclusion, profiling, translation and
      publication process.</para>
      <para>We maintained a library of build scripts to handle the build process. Each
      major documentation project then had its own master build script, that called on
      the build scripts library to publish the required outputs for each document in the
      required languages.</para>
      <para>These build scripts have not been released as part of the PACBook project.
      A full description of the build scripts is outside the scope of this article.
      However, in most cases the build process carried out the following steps, as
      illustrated in <xref linkend="paper-4_build_process"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="paper-4_build_process">
        <title>Build process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/2016_build_process.svg" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Transclude document modules into the assembly document.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If required, translate the complete document to a single specified
          language.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Validate the translated document.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Perform conditional profiling.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Perform any final steps and convert to the output format.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <note>
        <para>It’s necessary to validate the document after translation, as translated
        elements include inline markup. Any errors in the inline markup will be copied
        into the translated document.</para>
      </note>
      <para>We also use separate build scripts to handle the translation and conversion
      of images. These are called from the master build script for a particular
      documentation project.</para>
      <para>Within the image build scripts, we use the Apache Batik SVG Rasterizer
      <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://xmlgraphics.apache.org/batik/tools/rasterizer.html"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote> to convert translated SVG files into the formats required for
      publication, e.g. PNG.</para>
      <para>There’s no intrinsic reason why the build process has to be written in Apache
      Ant. Since each step involves an XML document, and the output of each step becomes
      the input of the next step, the ideal solution is probably an XProc pipeline
      <biblioref linkend="paper-4_xproc"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-4_conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para>This article outlined a solution that STANLEY Black and Decker Innovations
    developed to enable dynamic translation of XML documentation using XLIFF files,
    and to find the correct translations for each translatable element when the XML
    documentation consists of modular document source files that are transcluded into a
    single document.</para>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_conclusion_benefits">
      <title>Benefits</title>
      <para>The solution outlined in this article was used successfully within STANLEY
      Black and Decker Innovations over several years to handle document translation and
      to manage XLIFF files. However, as an in-house project, the XSLT stylesheets have
      not had the benefit of scrutiny from outside users.</para>
      <para>The solution gives a great deal of freedom to authors to create their own
      strategy for associating XLIFF files with source documents. You could use single
      monolithic XLIFF files for all translations across all projects, or separate XLIFF
      files for every topic, or anything in between. Like any solution which allows
      linking or transclusion, it’s best for each author to find the right balance
      between content reuse and maintainability.</para>
      <para>The XLIFF files that were produced by this solution could be passed directly
      on to our translation house. More importantly, completed translations could be
      dropped into our documentation source control with very little intervention. This
      vastly minimised author effort, translation errors and the number of files to
      maintain. Translation costs were also reduced as common content and its associated
      translations could be shared more easily between several documents.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_conclusion_issues">
      <title>Issues</title>
      <para>The translation stylesheets currently find the correct XLIFF file for each
      translatable element by searching up through the XML element hierarchy to find the
      nearest ancestor element that contains a translation statement. We’d also like
      to be able to associate translation statements with a particular part of the
      document by using the <tag class="attribute">rdf:about</tag> attribute to refer to
      an element’s <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attribute. This is not yet
      implemented.</para>
      <para>The markup was originally designed for DocBook XML and SVG. Some work would
      be required to adapt it for different documentation standards, such as HTML
      <biblioref linkend="paper-4_html"/>. The markup could easily be adapted to work with
      HTML 5, perhaps using <tag class="attribute">data</tag> attributes. We haven't
      investigated how the linked translation data could be adapted to work with
      HTML 5.</para>
      <para>The stylesheets were written in XSLT 1.0 and EXSLT <biblioref linkend="paper-4_exslt"/>. This is because at first we performed the transformations using
      xsltproc <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://xmlsoft.org/XSLT/xsltproc2.html"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote>, which doesn’t support later versions of XSLT. We later migrated to
      Saxon <footnote>
        <simpara>
          <link xl:href="http://www.saxonica.com"/>
        </simpara>
      </footnote> to perform XSLT transformations, so it should be possible to migrate
      the stylesheets to XSLT 2.0 or XLST 3.0, which may make some of the XSLT code
      simpler.</para>
      <para>The solution as described is designed to work with large scale, context-free
      transclusion, i.e. transcluding chapters or sections, which are then translated
      after transclusion. Small-scale, parametrised transclusion, i.e. transcluding words
      or phrases, raises an entirely different set of linguistic problems, which this
      article does not attempt to address. However, the PACBook project includes further
      markup and stylesheets which attempt to solve the linguistic problems associated
      with parametrised transclusion. For more information, see the PACBook repository on
      GitHub.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="paper-4_conclusion_future">
      <title>Future Development</title>
      <para>To finish on a personal note: Stanley Black and Decker Innovations was wound
      down at the end of July 2015, although I’ve continued to do documentation work
      with Stanley Black and Decker. I’ve cloned the PACBook GitHub repository
      at <link xl:href="https://github.com/janiveer/PACBook"/>, so that
      development on the project can continue. I’d be very interested to make contact
      with people who are working in similar areas and would be interested in
      collaboration. If anyone would like to contribute, please contact the
      author.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <bibliography xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>References</title>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_xliff">
      <abbrev>XLIFF</abbrev>
      <title>XLIFF Version 1.2</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://docs.oasis-open.org/xliff/v1.2/os/xliff-core.html</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <orgname>OASIS XML Localisation Interchange File Format (XLIFF) Technical
          Committee</orgname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>OASIS Standard</publishername>
      <pubdate>1 February 2008</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-04</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_gettext">
      <abbrev>gettext</abbrev>
      <title>GNU gettext 0.19.7</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">https://www.gnu.org/software/gettext/manual/index.html</biblioid>
      <publishername>Free Software Foundation</publishername>
      <pubdate>28 December 2015</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-04-26</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_docbook">
      <abbrev>DocBook</abbrev>
      <title>The DocBook Schema Version 5.0</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://docs.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs/docbook-5.0-spec-os.html</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <orgname>DocBook Technical Committee</orgname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>OASIS Standard</publishername>
      <pubdate>1 November 2009</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2014-03-09</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_rng">
      <abbrev>RELAX NG</abbrev>
      <title>RELAX NG Specification</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/relax-ng/spec-20011203.html</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>James Clark</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Murata Makoto</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>OASIS Committee Specification</publishername>
      <pubdate>3 December 2001</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-05-03</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_mallard">
      <abbrev>Mallard</abbrev>
      <title>Mallard 1.0</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://projectmallard.org/1.0/index</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname>Shaun McCance</personname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Jim Campbell</personname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>Project Mallard</publishername>
      <pubdate>23 July 2013</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2014-03-09</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_svg">
      <abbrev>SVG</abbrev>
      <title>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1 (Second Edition)</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>Erik Dahlström, et al</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
      <pubdate>16 August 2011</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-5</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_ibm">
      <abbrev>IBM</abbrev>
      <title>XML in localisation: Use XLIFF to translate documents</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/x-localis2</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname>Rodolfo Raya</personname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>IBM developerWorks</publishername>
      <pubdate>22 October 2004</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-02-06</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_tektronix">
      <abbrev>Tektronix</abbrev>
      <title>Improving Localization Process at Tektronix Using XML and XLIFF: A Case
      Study</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.moravia.com/files/download/Improving_Localization_Process_at_Tektronix_Using_XML_and_XLIFF.pdf</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname>Anette Hauswirth</personname>
          <affiliation>
            <orgname>Moravia Worldwide</orgname>
          </affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Bryan Schnabel</personname>
          <affiliation>
            <orgname>Tektronix</orgname>
          </affiliation>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>11 January 2008</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-02-06</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_yelp">
      <abbrev>Yelp</abbrev>
      <title>Introduction to Mallard: Build System Integration</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://en.flossmanuals.net/introduction-to-mallard/build-system-integration</biblioid>
      <publishername>FLOSS Manuals</publishername>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-02-06</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_xproc">
      <abbrev>XProc</abbrev>
      <title>XProc: An XML Pipeline Language</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/xproc</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>Norman Walsh</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Alex Milowski</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Henry S. Thompson</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
      <pubdate>11 May 2010</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2014-03-09</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_xslt10">
      <abbrev>XSLT</abbrev>
      <title>XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 1.0</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>James Clark</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
      <pubdate>16 November 1999</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2014-03-09</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_exslt">
      <abbrev>EXSLT</abbrev>
      <title>EXSLT</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://exslt.org</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname>Jeni Tennison</personname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Uche Ogbuji</personname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Jim Fuller</personname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Dave Pawson, et al</personname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>14 October 2003</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-05-03</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_its">
      <abbrev>ITS</abbrev>
      <title>Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 2.0</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/its20</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>David Filip, et al</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
      <pubdate>29 October 2013</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-04</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_bibo">
      <abbrev>BIBO</abbrev>
      <title>Bibliographic Ontology Specification Revision 1.3</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://bibliontology.com</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname>Bruce D’Arcus</personname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <personname>Frédérick Giasson</personname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>Structured Dynamics</publishername>
      <pubdate>4 November 2009</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-05</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_vivo">
      <abbrev>VIVO</abbrev>
      <title>VIVO-ISF Ontology version 1.6</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://vivoweb.org</biblioid>
      <publishername>Open Research Information Framework</publishername>
      <pubdate>13 December 2013</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-05</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_rdfxml">
      <abbrev>RDF/XML</abbrev>
      <title>RDF 1.1 XML Syntax</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-syntax-grammar</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>Fabien Gandon</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Guus Schreiber</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>W3C Recommendation</publishername>
      <pubdate>25 February 2014</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-05</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_html">
      <abbrev>HTML</abbrev>
      <title>HTML5</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.w3.org/TR/html</biblioid>
      <authorgroup>
        <editor>
          <personname>Ian Hickson</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Robin Berjon</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Steve Faulkner</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Travis Leithead</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Erika Doyle Navara</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Edward O’Connor</personname>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <personname>Silvia Pfeiffer</personname>
        </editor>
      </authorgroup>
      <publishername>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</publishername>
      <pubdate>28 October 2014</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-05</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-4_lgpl">
      <abbrev>LGPL</abbrev>
      <title>GNU Lesser General Public License Version 3</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html</biblioid>
      <publishername>Free Software Foundation, Inc.</publishername>
      <pubdate>29 June 2007</pubdate>
      <bibliomisc>Accessed 2016-03-05</bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
  <acknowledgements xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <para>Faenza icons by Matthieu James <footnote>
      <simpara>
        <link xl:href="https://launchpad.net/~tiheum"/>
      </simpara>
    </footnote>.</para>
  </acknowledgements>
</article>