<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="paper-2" version="5.0">
  <info xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Parse Earley, Parse Often</title>
    <subtitle>How to Parse Anything to XML</subtitle>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Steven</firstname>
        <surname>Pemberton</surname>
      </personname>
      <affiliation>
        <org>
          <orgname>CWI, Amsterdam</orgname>
        </org>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <abstract>
      <para>Invisible XML, ixml for short, is a generic technique for treating
        any parsable format as if it were XML, and thus allowing any parsable
        object to be injected into an XML pipeline. Based on the observation
        that XML can just be seen as the description of a parse-tree, any
        document can be parsed, and then serialised as XML. The parsing can also
        be undone, thus allowing roundtripping.</para>
      <para>This paper discusses issues around grammar design, and in particular
        parsing algorithms used to recognise any document, and converting the
        resultant parse-tree into XML, and gives a new perspective on a classic
        algorithm.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>What if you could see everything as XML? XML has many strengths for
      data exchange, strengths both inherent in the nature of XML markup and
      strengths that derive from the ubiquity of tools that can process XML. For
      authoring, however, other forms are preferred: no one writes CSS or
      Javascript in XML.</para>

    <para>It does not follow, however, that there is no value in representing
      such information in XML. Invisible XML <xref linkend="paper-2_IXML1"/>
      <xref linkend="paper-2_IXML2"/>, is a generic technique for treating any
      (context-free) parsable document as if it were XML, enabling authors to
      write in a format they prefer while providing XML for processes that are
      more effective with XML content. There is really no reason why XML cannot
      be more ubiquitous than it is.</para>

    <para>Ixml is based on the observation that XML can just be seen as the
      description of a parse-tree, and so any document can be parsed, and
      serialised as XML.</para>

    <para>Thus can a piece of CSS such as</para>

    <programlisting language="css">body {
  color: blue;
  font-weight: bold;
}</programlisting>

    <para>with ixml be read by an XML system as</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;css&gt;
  &lt;rule&gt;
    &lt;selector&gt;body&lt;/selector&gt;
    &lt;block&gt;
      &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;color&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;blue&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;font-weight&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;bold&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/block&gt;
  &lt;/rule&gt;
&lt;/css&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>or as</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;css&gt;
  &lt;rule&gt;
    &lt;selector&gt;body&lt;/selector&gt;
    &lt;block&gt;
      &lt;property name="color" value="blue"/&gt;
      &lt;property name="font-weight" value="bold"/&gt;
    &lt;/block&gt;
  &lt;/rule&gt;
&lt;/css&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The choice is yours. Similarly an arithmetic expression such as</para>

    <programlisting>a×(3+b)</programlisting>

    <para>can be read as</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;expr&gt;
  &lt;prod&gt;
    &lt;letter&gt;a&lt;/letter&gt;
    &lt;sum&gt;
      &lt;digit&gt;3&lt;/digit&gt;
      &lt;letter&gt;b&lt;/letter&gt;
    &lt;/sum&gt;
  &lt;/prod&gt;
&lt;/expr&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>and a URL such as</para>

    <programlisting>http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/xhtml.html</programlisting>

    <para>could be read as</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;uri&gt;
  &lt;scheme&gt;http&lt;/scheme&gt;
  &lt;authority&gt;
    &lt;host&gt;
      &lt;sub&gt;www&lt;/sub&gt;
      &lt;sub&gt;w3&lt;/sub&gt;
      &lt;sub&gt;org&lt;/sub&gt;
    &lt;/host&gt;
  &lt;/authority&gt;
  &lt;path&gt;
    &lt;seg&gt;TR&lt;/seg&gt;
    &lt;seg&gt;1999&lt;/seg&gt;
    &lt;seg&gt;xhtml.html&lt;/seg&gt;
  &lt;/path&gt;
&lt;/uri&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Previous presentations on ixml have centred on the basics, the design
      of grammars, and round-tripping back to the original form. This paper
      discusses a suitable parsing algorithm, and gives a new perspective on a
      classic algorithm.</para>

  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Parsing</title>
    <para>Parsing is a process of taking an essentially linear form, recognising
      the underlying structure, and transforming the input to a form that
      expresses that structure. The fact that the resulting structure is
      represented by a tree means that converting it to XML is a relatively
      simple matter.</para>

    <para>There are many parsing algorithms with different properties such as
      speed, run-time complexity, and space usage <xref linkend="paper-2_AHO"/>. One of
      the most popular is LL1 parsing; in particular, the "1" in this name
      refers to the fact that you can parse based only on the knowledge of the
      next symbol in the input, thus simplifying parsing.</para>
    <para>Consider the following example of a grammar describing a simple
      programming language.</para>
    <para>A grammar consists of a number of 'rules', each rule consisting, in
      this notation, of a name of the rule, a colon, and a definition describing
      the structure of the thing so named, followed by a full stop. The
      structure can consist of one or more 'alternatives', in this notation
      separated by semicolons. Each alternative consists of a sequence of
      'nonterminals' and 'terminals' separated by commas. Nonterminals are
      defined by subsequent rules; terminals, enclosed in quotes, are literal
      characters that have to be matched in the input.</para>

    <programlisting>program: block.
block: "{", statements, "}".
statements: statement, ";", statements; empty.
statement: if statement; while statement;
           assignment; call; block.
if statement: "if", condition, "then", statement,
               else-option.
else-option: "else", statement; empty.
empty: .
while statement: "while", condition, "do",
                 statement.
assignment: variable, "=", expression.
call: identifier, "(", parameters, ")".
parameters: expression, parameter-tail; empty.
parameter-tail: ",", expression, parameter-tail;
                empty.</programlisting>

    <para>This grammar is almost but not quite LL1. The problem is that the
      rules 'assignment' and 'call' both start with the same symbol (an
      identifier), and so you can't tell which rule to process just by looking
      at the next symbol.</para>

    <para>However, the language is LL1. This can be shown by combining and
      rewriting the rules for assignment and call:</para>

    <programlisting>statement: if statement; while statement;
           assignment-or-call; block.
assignment-or-call: identifier, tail.
tail: assignment-tail; call-tail.
assignment-tail: "=", expression.
call-tail: "(", parameters, ")".</programlisting>

    <para>Now the decision on which rule to use can be taken purely based on the
      next symbol.</para>

    <para>One of the reasons that LL1 parsing is popular, is that it is easy to
      translate it directly to a program. For instance:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">procedure program = { block; }
procedure block = { expect("{"); statements;
                    expect("}")}
procedure statements = {
  if nextsym in statement-starters
  then {
    statement;
    expect(";");
    statements;
  }
}
procedure statement = { 
  if nextsym="if" then ifstatement;
  else if nextsym="while" then whilestatement;
  else if nextsym=identifier
    then assignment-or-call;
  else if nextsym="{" then block;
  else error("syntax error");
}</programlisting>

    <para>etc. (This example is much simplified from what an industrial-strength
      parser would do, but demonstrates the principles).</para>

    <para>However, rather than writing the parser as code, you can just as
      easily write what could be seen as an interpreter for a grammar. For
      instance:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">procedure parserule(alts) = {
  if (some alt in alts has nextsym in starters(alt))
    then parsealt(alt);
  else if (some alt in alts has empty(alt)
    then do-nothing;
  else error("syntax error");
}
procedure parsealt(alt) = {
  for term in alt do {
    if nonterm(term) then parserule(def(term));
    else expectsym(term);
  }
}</programlisting>

    <para>One disadvantage of LL1 parsing is that no rule may be left-recursive.
      For instance, if the rule for 'statements' above were rewritten as</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">statements: statements, statement, ";"; empty.</programlisting>

    <para>this could not be parsed using LL1. It is easy to see why if you
      convert this to code, since the procedure would be:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">procedure statements = {
  if nextsym in statement-starts {
    statements;
    statement;
    expect (";");
  }
}</programlisting>

    <para>in other words, it would go into an infinite recursive loop. In the
      case of a statement list, there is no problem with expressing it as a
      right-recursive rule. However, there are cases where it matters. For
      example, with subtraction:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">subtraction: number; subtraction, "-", number.</programlisting>

    <para>If we rewrite this as</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">subtraction: number; number, "-", subtraction.</programlisting>

    <para>then an expression such as</para>

    <programlisting>3-2-1</programlisting>

    <para>would mean in the first case</para>

    <programlisting>((3-2)-1)</programlisting>

    <para>and in the second</para>

    <programlisting>(3-(2-1))</programlisting>

    <para>which has a different meaning.</para>

    <para>To overcome this problem, grammars that are to be parsed with LL1
      methods must have a notation to express repetition. For instance:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">statements: (statement, ";")*.
subtraction: number, ("-", number)*.</programlisting>

    <para>which can be translated to procedures like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-earley">procedure subtraction = {
  number;
  while (nextsym="-") do {
    skipsym;
    number;
  }
}</programlisting>

    <para>Another disadvantage of LL1 and related techniques is that there has
      to be an initial lexical analysis phase, where 'symbols' are first
      recognised and classified. If not, then the level of terminal symbols that
      are available to the parser are the base characters, such as letters and
      digits, etc., meaning that for instance if the next character is an "i"
      you can't tell if that starts an identifier, or the word "if".</para>

    <para>Finally, a problem with these techniques is the need to understand the
      LL1 conditions, express a grammar in such a way that they are satisfied,
      and the need to have a checker that determines if the grammar indeed
      satisfies the conditions before using it <xref linkend="paper-2_LL1"/>
      <xref linkend="paper-2_GRAMMAR"/>.</para>

  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>General Parsing</title>

    <para>To summarise the advantages of LL1 parsing: it is fast, its run-time
      complexity is low, proportional only to the length of the input, and it is
      easy to express as a program.</para>

    <para>However the disadvantages are that it can only handle a certain class
      of restricted languages, it requires the author of a grammar to understand
      the restrictions and rewrite grammars so that they match, and it requires
      a lexical pre-processing stage.</para>

    <para>To overcome these disadvantages we have to consider more general
      parsing techniques.</para>

    <para>One classic example is that of Earley <xref linkend="paper-2_EARLEY"/>, which
      can parse any grammar, for any language. (There is actually one
      restriction, that the language is context-free, but since we are only
      using grammars that express context-free languages, the issue doesn't
      apply here).</para>

    <para>Although the Earley algorithm is well-known, it is apparently
      less-often used. One reason this may be so is because the run-time
      complexity of Earley is rather poor in the worst case, namely O(n³).
      However, what potential users who are put off by this number do not seem
      to realise is that it is a function of the language being parsed, and not
      the method itself. For LL1 grammars, Earley is also O(n), just like pure
      LL1 parsers.</para>

    <para>So what does Earley do?</para>
  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Pseudo-parallelism</title>
    <para>Modern operating systems run programs by having many simultaneously in
      store simultaneously (242 on the computer this text is being written on),
      and allocating brief periods of time (a fraction of a second) to each in
      turn. A program once allocated a slot is allowed to run until it reaches
      the end of its execution, its time allocation runs out, or the program
      asks to do an operation that can't be immediately satisfied (such as
      accessing the disk). Programs that are ready to run are added to one or
      more queues of jobs, and at the end of the next time slot a program is
      selected from the queues, based on priority, and then allowed to run for
      the next slot. Because the time slots are so short by human measure, this
      approach gives the impression of the programs running simultaneously in
      parallel.</para>
    <para>Earley operates similarly. Just as the example earlier, it is an
      interpreter for grammars, with the exception that when a rule is selected
      to be run, all of its alternatives are queued to run 'in parallel'. When
      an alternative is given a slot, it is allowed to do exactly one task, one
      of:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>note that it has nothing more to do and restart its parent (that
          is, terminating successfully)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>start a new nonterminal process (and wait until that completes
          successfully)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>match a single terminal (and requeue itself)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>note that it cannot match the next symbol, and effectively
          terminate unsuccessfully.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The queue contains each task with the position in the input that it is
      at. The queue is ordered on input position, so that earlier input
      positions get priority. In this way only a small part of the input stream
      needs to be present in memory.</para>

    <para>There is one other essential feature: when a rule starts up, its name
      and position is recorded in a trace before being queued. If the same rule
      is later started at the same position, it is not queued, since it is
      either already being processed, or has already been processed: we already
      know or will know the result of running that task at that position. This
      has two advantages: one is pure optimisation, since the same identical
      process will never be run twice; but more importantly, this overcomes the
      problem with infinite recursion that we saw with LL1 parsers.</para>

    <para>To take an example, suppose the rule <code>statement</code> is being
      processed at the point in the input where we have the text</para>

    <programlisting>a=0;</programlisting>

    <para>Processing <code>statement</code> mean that its alternatives get
      queued: namely <code>if statement</code>, <code>while statement</code>,
        <code>assignment</code>, <code>call</code>, and
      <code>block</code>.</para>

    <para>With the exception of <code>assignment</code> and <code>call</code>,
      all of these fail immediately because the first symbol in the input fails
      to match the initial item in the alternative.</para>

    <para>Assignment and call both have as first item '<code>identifier</code>'.
        <code>Identifier</code> gets queued (once) and succeeds with the input
      'a', so both alternatives get requeued. Since the next symbol is '=',
        <code>call</code> fails, and <code>assignment</code> gets requeued (and
      eventually succeeds).</para>
  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>The structure of tasks</title>
    <para>Each task that gets queued has the following structure:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The name of the rule that this alternative is a part of (e.g.
          statement);</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The position in the input that it started;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The position that it is currently at;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The list of items in the alternative that have so far been
          successfully parsed, with their start position;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The list of items still to be processed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>When a task is requeued, its important parts are its current position,
      and the list of items still to be processed. If the list of items still to
      be processed is empty, then the task has completed, successfully.</para>
  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Earley</title>

    <para>So now with these preliminaries behind us, let us look at the Earley
      parser (here expressed in ABC <xref linkend="paper-2_ABC"/>):</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">HOW TO PARSE input WITH grammar:
INITIALISE
START grammar FOR start.symbol grammar AT start.pos
WHILE more.tasks:
 TAKE task
 SELECT:
  finished task:
   CONTINUE PARENTS task
  ELSE:
   PUT next.symbol task, position task IN sym, pos
   SELECT:
    grammar nonterminal sym:
     START grammar FOR sym AT pos
    sym starts (input, pos): \Terminal, matches
     RECORD TERMINAL input FOR task
     CONTINUE task AT (pos incremented (input, sym))
    ELSE:
     PASS \Terminal, doesn't match</programlisting>

    <para>So let us analyse this code line-by-line:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">START grammar FOR start.symbol grammar AT start.pos</programlisting>

    <para>All grammars have a top-level start symbol, such as
        <code>program</code> for the example programming language grammar. This
      line adds all the alternatives of the rule for the start symbol to the
      queue.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">WHILE more.tasks:</programlisting>

    <para>While the queue of tasks is not empty, we loop through the following
      steps.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">TAKE task</programlisting>

    <para>Take the first task from the queue.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">SELECT:</programlisting>

    <para>There are two possibilities: the rule has nothing more to do, and so
      terminates successfully, or there are still symbols to process.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">finished task:
  CONTINUE PARENTS task</programlisting>

    <para>The task has nothing more to do, so all the parents of this task (the
      rules that initiated it) are requeued.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">ELSE:</programlisting>

    <para>Otherwise this task still has to be processed.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">PUT next.symbol task, position task IN sym, pos</programlisting>

    <para>We take the next symbol (terminal or nonterminal) that still has to be
      processed, and the current position in the input we are at.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">SELECT:</programlisting>

    <para>The next symbol is either a nonterminal or a terminal.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">grammar nonterminal sym:
  START grammar FOR sym AT pos</programlisting>

    <para>The symbol is a nonterminal, so we queue all its alternatives to be
      processed at the current position.</para>

    <para>Otherwise it is a terminal:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">sym starts (input, pos): \Terminal, matches
  RECORD TERMINAL input FOR task
  CONTINUE task AT (pos incremented (input, sym))</programlisting>

    <para>If the symbol matched the input at the current position, then we
      record the match in the trace, and requeue the current task after
      incrementing its position past the matched characters.</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">ELSE:
  PASS</programlisting>

    <para>Finally, it was a terminal, but didn't match the next symbol in the
      input, and so the task doesn't get requeued, and so effectively terminates
      (unsuccessfully).</para>

  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

    <title>The Trace</title>

    <para>The result of a parse is the trace, which is the list, for all
      positions in the input where a task was (re-)started, of the tasks that
      were (re-)started there. This is the list that is used to prevent
      duplicate tasks being started at the same position, but also effectively
      records the results of the parse.</para>

    <para>So for instance, here is an example trace for the very first position
      in the input (before dealing with any input characters), for the example
      grammar:</para>

    <programlisting>program[1.1:1.1]: | block
block[1.1:1.1]: | "{" statements "}" </programlisting>

    <para>Two rules have been started, one for program, and consequently one for
      block.</para>

    <para>The positions have been recorded as
        <code>line-number.character-number</code>, and here represent the
      position where we started from, and the position up to which we have
      processed for this rule, in this case, both of them
      <code>1.1</code>.</para>

    <para>After the colon are two lists, the items in the respective rule that
      have already been processed (none yet in this case), and the items still
      to be processed, the two separated in this output by a vertical
      bar.</para>

    <para>In parsing a very simple program, namely <code>{a=0;}</code>, after
      parsing the first opening brace, this will be in the trace:</para>

    <programlisting>block[1.1:1.2]: "{"[:1.2] | statements "}"</programlisting>

    <para>signifying that we have parsed up to position 1.2, and that we have
      parsed the open brace, which ends at 1.2.</para>

    <para>Later still, after we have parsed the semicolon we will find in the
      trace</para>

    <programlisting>block[1.1:1.6]: "{"[:1.2] statements[:1.6] | "}"</programlisting>

    <para>which signifies we have matched the opening brace up to position 1.2,
      something that matches 'statements' up to 1.6, and there only remains a
      closing brace to match.</para>

    <para>And finally at the end, we will find</para>

    <programlisting>block[1.1:2.1]: "{[:1.2] statements[:1.6] "}[:2.1] </programlisting>

    <para>which since the 'to do' list is empty signifies a successful parse
      from position 1.1 to 2.1.</para>

    <para>Since it is only completed (sub-)parses that we are interested in,
      here is the complete trace of all successful sub-parses for the program
        <code>{a=0;}</code>:</para>

    <programlisting>1.1
1.2
  empty[1.2:1.2]: | 
  statements[1.2:1.2]: empty[:1.2] | 
1.3
  identifier[1.2:1.3]: "a"[:1.3] | 
  variable[1.2:1.3]: identifier[:1.3] | 
1.4
1.5
  assignment[1.2:1.5]: variable[:1.3] "="[:1.4] expression[:1.5] | 
  statement[1.2:1.5]: assignment[:1.5] | 
  expression[1.4:1.5]: number[:1.5] | 
  number[1.4:1.5]: "0"[:1.5] | 
1.6
  statements[1.2:1.6]: statement[:1.5] ";"[:1.6] statements[:1.6] | 
  empty[1.6:1.6]: | 
  statements[1.6:1.6]: empty[:1.6] | 
2.1
  block[1.1:2.1]: "{"[:1.2] statements[:1.6] "}"[:2.1] | 
  program[1.1:2.1]: block[:2.1] |</programlisting>

  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Serialising the Parse Tree</title>

    <para>So the task of serialising the trace, is one of looking at the list in
      the trace for the last position in the input for a successful parse for
      the top level symbol of the grammar, and working from there
      downwards:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">SERIALISE start.symbol grammar
          FROM &lt;start position&gt; TO &lt;end position&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>where the procedure SERIALISE looks like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="pemberton-abc">HOW TO SERIALISE name FROM start TO end:
  IF SOME task IN trace[end] HAS
    (symbol task = name AND finished task AND
     start.position task = start): 
    WRITE "&lt;", name, "&gt;"
    CHILDREN
    WRITE "&lt;/", name, "&gt;"
CHILDREN: 
  PUT start IN newstart
  FOR (sym, pos) IN done task: 
    SELECT: 
      terminal sym: WRITE sym
      ELSE: 
        SERIALISE sym FROM newstart TO pos
    PUT pos IN newstart</programlisting>

    <para>For our example program, this will produce:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;program&gt;
  &lt;block&gt;{&lt;statements&gt;
      &lt;statement&gt;
        &lt;assignment&gt;
          &lt;variable&gt;
            &lt;identifier&gt;a&lt;/identifier&gt;
          &lt;/variable&gt;=&lt;expression&gt;
            &lt;number&gt;0&lt;/number&gt;
          &lt;/expression&gt;
        &lt;/assignment&gt;
      &lt;/statement&gt;;&lt;statements&gt;
        &lt;empty/&gt;
      &lt;/statements&gt;
    &lt;/statements&gt;}&lt;/block&gt;
&lt;/program&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The simple task of adapting this to the exact needs of ixml as
      described in earlier papers is left as an exercise for the reader.</para>

  </section>

  <section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>The power of XML has been the simple and consistent representation of
      data, allowing widespread interoperability.</para>

    <para>What ixml shows is that with a simple front-end, XML can be made even
      more powerful by making all parsable documents accessible to the XML
      pipeline.</para>
  </section>

  <bibliography xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>References</title>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_IXML1" xreflabel="[1]">
      <abbrev>1</abbrev>
      <title>Invisible XML</title>
      <biblioid class="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol10.Pemberton01</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Steven</firstname>
          <surname>Pemberton</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <bibliomisc>Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference</bibliomisc>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Balisage</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <address>Montréal, Canada</address>
      <pubdate>August 6 - 9, 2013</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_IXML2" xreflabel="[2]">
      <abbrev>2</abbrev>
      <title>Data just wants to be (format) neutral</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://archive.xmlprague.cz/2016/files/xmlprague-2016-proceedings.pdf#page=121</biblioid>
      <pagenums>109-120</pagenums>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Steven</firstname>
          <surname>Pemberton</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>XML Prague</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <address>Prague, Czech Republic</address>
      <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_AHO" xreflabel="[3]">
      <abbrev>3</abbrev>
      <title>The Theory of Parsing, Translation, and Compiling</title>
      <biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0139145567</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Alfred</firstname>
          <honorific>V</honorific>
          <surname>Aho</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Jeffrey</firstname>
          <honorific>D</honorific>
          <surname>Ullman</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <publishername>Prentice-Hall</publishername>
      <pubdate>1972</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_LL1" xreflabel="[4]">
      <abbrev>4</abbrev>
      <title>Grammar Tools</title>
      <biblioid class="uri">http://www.cwi.nl/~steven/abc/examples/grammar.html</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Steven</firstname>
          <surname>Pemberton</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <pubdate>1991</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_GRAMMAR" xreflabel="[5]">
      <abbrev>5</abbrev>
      <title>A Syntax Improving Program</title>
      <biblioid class="doi">10.1093/comjnl/11.1.31</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>J</firstname>
          <honorific>M</honorific>
          <surname>Foster</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Computer Journal</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <volumenum>11</volumenum>
      <issuenum>1</issuenum>
      <pagenums>31-34</pagenums>
      <pubdate>1967</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_EARLEY" xreflabel="[6]">
      <abbrev>6</abbrev>
      <title>An Efficient Context-Free Parsing Algorithm</title>
      <biblioid class="doi">10.1145/362007.362035</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Jay</firstname>
          <surname>Earley</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry xml:id="paper-2_ABC" xreflabel="[7]">
      <abbrev>7</abbrev>
      <title>The ABC Programmer's Handbook</title>
      <biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-13-000027-2</biblioid>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Leo</firstname>
          <surname>Geurts</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Lambert</firstname>
          <surname>Meertens</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Steven</firstname>
          <surname>Pemberton</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <publishername>Prentice-Hall</publishername>
      <pubdate>1990</pubdate>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
</article>
