<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="paper-24" version="5.0">
    <info xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
        <title> What you need to know about the Maths Stack</title>
        <subtitle>MathML, MathJax, HTML5, and EPUB 3</subtitle>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <honorific>Ms</honorific>
                    <firstname>Autumn</firstname>
                    <surname>Cuellar</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>Design Science</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <honorific>Mr</honorific>
                    <firstname>Paul</firstname>
                    <surname>Topping</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>Design Science</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <editor>
            <personname>
                <honorific>Mr</honorific>
                <firstname>Bob</firstname>
                <surname>Mathews</surname>
            </personname>
        </editor>

        <orgname>Design Science, Inc.</orgname>

        <address>
            <city>Long Beach</city><state>CA</state>
            <street>140 Pine Ave. 4th Floor</street>
            <postcode>90803</postcode>
            <country>USA</country>
        </address>

        <abstract><para>MathML is a well-known and widely-used standard for encoding mathematics
            within XML workflows, but what you may not know is that MathML is not just a
            standard that affects your internal workflow, used only for storage and
            converted to images when you need to present your content to your audience.
            MathML is a key part of the digital publishing revolution towards enriched
            content. Its recent inclusion into the HTML5 and EPUB 3 standards is helping to
            bring to fruition the promise of interactive content for maths-based industries
            around the world.</para>
            <para>All of the major browser vendors have pledged support for HTML5, and many EPUB
                readers are built on browser engines, thus full browser and e-reader support of
                MathML is expected in the future. Gecko-based browsers including Firefox already do
                include native MathML support. WebKit, the engine behind Safari and Chrome, also has
                some MathML support, though only Safari has included this feature in releases. Until
                universal support for MathML is available, <link xlink:href="http://www.mathjax.org">MathJax</link> fills in the gaps. MathJax is an open-source Javascript library
                for displaying MathML in all modern browsers and has been included with success in
                EPUB readers, such as Readium. </para>
            <para>MathJax helps both content creators and content consumers realize the full
                advantages of MathML. One challenge that producers of digital content are faced with
                is the range of devices, screen sizes, and screen resolutions that must be
                supported. Unlike with bitmap images, MathJax easily adjusts equations to match the
                surrounding text without losing any quality. MathJax also leaves the MathML content
                available for re-use. This is particularly important to audiences who'd like to play
                with the equations in your content by loading (such as through copy and paste) the
                equations into Microsoft Excel or other calculation or modeling software, most of
                which accept MathML as an input format. Another feature of MathML that MathJax
                accommodates is its accessibility to audiences with vision and learning
                disabilities. MathML has been embraced by these communities and most accessible
                technology software includes support of MathML by reading the equation aloud,
                highlighting parts of the expression, and allowing control of the navigation of the
                equation. Finally, by leaving the MathML in the content, the equations remain
                searchable, allowing your content to be found. </para>
            <para>The key elements to moving your maths forward into this bright new interactive
                publication era are a base doctype that allows MathML, tools to create MathML, XSL,
                and MathJax. Many standard doctypes already include MathML or are on their way to
                adding MathML support. OASIS, for example, keeps a <link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs/wd-docbook-mathml-1.1CR1.html">DocBook MathML Document Type</link>, and the next version of DITA (1.3) will
                also include MathML. All other doctypes, since XML is the eXtensible Markup
                Language, can be extended to include MathML. Though MathML can be manually written,
                it's a verbose language that was never intended to be written by humans. To create
                MathML, you will need a conversion tool to convert existing maths content to MathML
                and/or a MathML editor, such as MathFlow. To publish the XML to its digital output
                format, HTML5 or EPUB 3, a wide range of publishing tools are available on the
                market, most of which use XSL in some part of the process. The XSL or publishing
                tool can usually be easily modified such that the output includes the MathJax
                libraries. Lastly, you will need the MathJax libraries.</para>
            <para>We are only just now starting to get a taste of the exciting future of digital
                content thanks to the HTML5 and EPUB 3 standards, and MathJax is filling the need of
                publishers with maths in their content until the browser and e-reader technology
                catches up to the standards. The benefits of MathML can only be fully realized when
                MathML is supported not just as an internal storage format but also as a delivery
                format, and with the Maths Stack, consisting of MathML, MathJax, HTML5, and EPUB 3,
                the maths in your digital publications are interoperable, accessible, and
                searchable. </para></abstract>
    </info>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
        <info>
            <title>Introduction</title>
        </info>
        <para>The digital publishing era promises to revolutionize how we consume content. Plain
            text is now being enhanced not only with images but also with, for example, video,
            music, and interactive applications. At the heart of this revolution in publishing is
            XML. Recent developments in XML-based standards, such as HTML5 and EPUB 3, are
            facilitating the trend towards enhanced content.</para>
        <para>The great news for those of us with any interest in scientific, technical,
            engineering, or mathematical (STEM) content is that mathematics, often an afterthought
            in web technologies, are a key part of the recent advancements toward enriched content.
            In this paper we'll discuss the latest developments in the XML standards for
            mathematics, web pages, and e-books; how MathML brings to fruition the promise of
            enhanced content for maths-based industries; the current status of support for these
            standards; and, finally, what you need to do to prepare your content for the bright new
            future of digital publishing.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
        <title>Recent Standards Developments</title>
        <sect2><title>MathML</title><para>MathML is the XML standard for encoding mathematical information. It's maintained by W3C, the
                same organization that maintains the XML and HTML standards. MathML was conceived in
                the mid-1990's during a discussion of requirements for HTML 3. HTML, the language
                behind the World Wide Web (a network built by scientists for scientists) at this
                time had no way to represent mathematics -- a failing that some felt needed to be
                addressed. However, the challenges for representing maths on the web seemed too
                mountainous to be tackled in an update to HTML, so the MathML working group was
                formed to address the problems surrounding maths in XML/HTML.</para>
            <para>The MathML 1 spec was finalized in 1998. Five years later, in 2003, MathML 2 was
                unveiled to correct flaws in the initial specification. For instance, in version 1,
                multi-line equations could only be expressed through the use of tables. MathML 2
                also favors certain features of Cascading Stylesheets (CSS), which had grown more
                popular for applying styles to content, over its former attributes for specifying
                key properties.</para>
            <para>MathML 3 was finalized in late 2010. With MathML 3, MathML shows a new maturity by
                taking into consideration the needs of various communities with a more specialized
                interest in mathematics. For example, the publishing industry is now served by
                taking line breaks to the next level: for long equations that may extend past the
                width of pages or columns, content providers can now specify both a maximum width
                (so the equation automatically wraps) as well as how to indent or align subsequent
                lines. For the education community, MathML 3 adds new features to support elementary
                math, such as stacked addition and substraction, long division, and repeating
                decimals. MathML 3 also became a truly international standard by adding support for
                right-to-left languages and for notations that vary from region to region.</para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>HTML5</title><para>While MathML has been developed and revised, it has established itself as a standard for
                encoding mathematics. It has been incorporated into a number of other standards from
                biological modeling languages (CellML and SBML) to medical journal archives (NLM).
                Tool support for MathML has advanced, with MathML import and/or export available
                from a variety of software applications ranging from word processors to computer
                algebra systems. Most importantly, from the perspective of the HTML Working Group,
                MathML rendering engines have arrived on the scene to provide expert layout of
                complex equations.</para>
            <para>Mathematics did not make the cut for inclusion into HTML3 due to the challenges of
                rendering a complicated and varied language. However, through MathML these
                challenges have been overcome. Thus, HTML5, which as of December 2012 is a W3C
                Candidate Recommendation, now includes MathML.</para>
            <para>HTML5 has been praised for its inclusion of different content types. In previous
                versions, different types of media (such as video, audio, math, and even images)
                were treated as external objects, many of which required plug-ins to the browser for
                the visitor to experience. The benefit of including media in the HTML is that
                browsers will consistently and correctly display the content without requiring
                external software. This means, theoretically, a given page with its included media
                will display the same on any platform or device.<xref linkend="paper-24_fernandes-2012"/></para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>EPUB 3</title><para>EPUB, the open standard for e-books, is maintained by the International Digital Publishing
                Forum (IDPF). In version 2 of the EPUB standard, the content of the e-book could be
                expressed in either of two varieties: DAISY or XHTML. DAISY is an independently
                managed standard for specifying Digital Talking Books, mostly used for accessibility
                purposes. Because the DAISY standard included MathML for specifying mathematical
                content, one could create a valid EPUB file with MathML.</para>
            <para>In the most recent version of the EPUB standard, IDPF eliminated the DAISY
                variant, based the XHTML variant on HTML5, and endorsed inclusion of MathML as an
                important aspect of e-books. Like HTML5, EPUB 3 has been lauded for taking digital
                content to the next level with its support for media.</para></sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><title>How MathML Fits in with the HTML/EPUB Promise of Enriched Content</title>
        <para>Maths content has long been included in e-books and web pages as images, plain text
            (often referred to as ASCII Math), or, for the enthusiasts, as TeX/LaTeX. However, by
            delivering the mathematics in your content as MathML, you can enable your audience new
            levels of interaction with the information presented. MathML is integral to HTML5's and
            EPUB 3's promises of enhanced publications. MathML offers the following advantages in
            usability and presentation over alternative formats.</para>
        <sect2><title>Searchability</title><para>Annually, EMC, a maker of storage and big data systems, publishes a study called "Digital
                Universe" measuring the amount of digital data available. By the end of 2012, EMC
                measured 2.5 zettabytes of data available worldwide. The study showed the amount of
                data available worldwide had doubled in just two years. The same study predicts that
                by 2020, the total data count will exceed 40 zettabytes. "To put it in perspective,
                40 zettabytes is 40 trillion gigabytes -- estimated to be 57 times the amount of all
                the grains of sand on all the beaches on earth." <xref linkend="paper-24_mearian-2012"/></para>
            <para>With so much data available at our fingertips, search is becoming ever more
                important. An ambition in the field of mathematics is how best to search
                mathematical notation. Maths search could have several applications including aiding
                research in scientific communities, helping identify common patterns between remote
                disciplines, and serving as an educational tool. <xref linkend="paper-24_miner-2004"/>
                Most of the studies that have had success in this area, such as MathDex, EgoMath,
                and MathWebWorld, have used alorithms relying on MathML. <xref linkend="paper-24_misutka-2008"/></para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>Localization</title><para>While maths is a universal language and semantically one expression might be the same as the
                next, the notation used to express a given equation might vary significantly from
                region to region. For instance, notation for expressing long division differs
                distinctly depending on where you are in the world. With XML stylesheets, one can
                target the display of mathematical content to the region where it's being
                observed.</para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>Flexibility of Display</title><para>Since MathML is a part of the document and is rendered at load time, environmental settings
                can be factored into the display of the maths. Therefore, if a visitor or reader has
                his browser or e-reader font size set to a larger font size than the default
                setting, the equations will also appear at the larger base font size. The audience
                will also see high quality equations no matter the resolution or pixel density of
                the device loading the web page or e-book. This is a special shortcoming of using
                images for maths display, as images intended for lower pixel density monitors
                display poorly on high pixel density monitors and vice versa. </para>
            <para>MathML, like XML, gives you power of presentation, allowing content providers to
                apply a certain style to equations along with the rest of the document without
                having to go through and change each equation individually. For example, equations
                in tables can be displayed at a smaller font size than the rest of the document or
                maths in change tracking systems can be highlighted with a foreground (or
                background) color to indicate changes to an expression.</para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>Accessibility</title>
            <para>Content providers may be required by government statute to supply accessible
                materials to readers with vision and learning disabilities, however, even if
                government regulations don't apply, there is no reason to limit the available
                audience. The accessibility community favors MathML because MathML's encoding of a
                mathematical expression is precise enough that it may be used to translate the
                equation to Braille or speech text and can also be used to navigate a complex
                equation so that parts of the equation can be repeated in a semantically relevant
                way. Most standards intended to support the accessibility community, including DAISY
                for Digital Talking Books and NIMAS for instructional materials, require maths to be
                encoded in MathML.</para></sect2>
        <sect2><title>Interoperability</title><para>Perhaps the most exciting feature of MathML is that it is receiving growing support in a wide
                variety of applications: computer algebra systems, graphing applications,
                calculators, modeling software, assessment creation systems, educational
                whiteboards, etc. Even today one can copy and paste (or import and export) MathML
                between applications to make better use of data. It isn't difficult to envision the
                future of MathML: Imagine a doctor is reading a journal article describing
                mathematical functions behind chemical pathways in the body. To help him visualize
                how changes in the level of sodium affect the pathways, he sends the equations in
                the journal article to a modeling system. Within seconds he is able to start
                adjustments until a life-saving solution is found. Alternatively, the journal
                article may include a simple modeling system that allows the reader to adjust the
                parameters of the mathematical functions in the article for hands-on reinforcement
                of the concepts being described. The potential for interoperability is only limited
                by the imagination.</para></sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><title>Status of MathML Support in HTML5 and EPUB 3</title><para>The vendors of the major browsers have been vocal in their support of HTML5. In fact, all of
            the browser vendors have representatives on the HTML Working Group. Support for MathML
            is already available in the Gecko rendering engine, which is used by Firefox. WebKit,
            the engine behind Safari, can render a subset of MathML. Opera currently uses CSS to
            provide support for MathML. As part of HTML5, browser support for MathML will no doubt
            only improve in the coming years.</para>
        <para>Since EPUB 3 is based on HTML5, and since many e-readers are built on browser
            technology, some e-readers have inherited MathML support. Apple's iBooks e-reader is a
            primary example. Based on WebKit, iBooks has limited support of MathML. With the
            enthusiasm that's been shown for EPUB 3, the backing of all of its major features,
            including MathML, is expected in future versions of all e-readers.</para>
        <para>However, knowing that support is coming is of little use to those who want to start
            taking advantage of all of the benefits of MathML today. With the gaps in browser and
            e-reader display of MathML today, this is an obstacle. No one wants to produce content
            so that the intended audience has to jump through hoops to view it. Without a doubt,
            every website visitor has been on the wrong end of content delivery requirements: a
            website might display a message stating that you do not have the required version of
            Flash or that the website is optimized for a certain version of browser, which is (of
            course) not the browser you are using. You are left to contemplate whether the content
            you have come to consume is worth the effort of updating software or switching browsers,
            and sometimes it's not.</para>
        <para>Luckily, a Javascript project called MathJax has been developed to eliminate the gaps
            in browser and e-reader support of MathML.</para><sect2><title>MathJax</title><para>MathJax is an open-source Javascript library for rendering MathML in all modern browsers. It
                is developed by a consortium consisting of Design Science, American Mathematical
                Society, and the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics. Internet Explorer
                and Google Chrome, two browsers that have no native support of MathML, using
                MathJax, can now display HTML5 pages with MathML in them without the use of a
                client-installed plug-in. It also adds more complete support of the MathML
                specification than Firefox, Safari, and Opera have alone.</para>
            <para>Because MathJax improves browser display of MathML, all e-readers built on browser
                technology can improve their EPUB 3 support by implementing the MathJax Javascript
                library. Calibre is a popular e-reader application that has already included MathJax
                to display e-books with mathematical content.</para></sect2></sect1>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><title>Enriching Content with MathML</title><para>Your excitement to get started with your maths stack is palpable. Without delving into too
            much technical detail, the four areas requiring consideration when setting up your maths
            stack are your doctype, MathML editors, the conversion process, and MathJax.</para>
        <para>Assuming you are working in a source format other than HTML5 or EPUB 3, first you'll
            want to make sure your XML doctype includes MathML. Some standard doctypes, such as
            Docbook and NLM, do already include MathML. If your doctype does not already, you'll
            need to modify your schema to include the MathML schema.</para>
        <para>Once your schema has been set up to include MathML, the next step is to start creating
            MathML. While MathML is human-readable, it's a verbose language that doesn't lend itself
            to manual creation. Quite possibly your XML editor of choice already includes a MathML
            editor or has a plug-in available for download. If not, Design Science offers a suite of
            MathML editors for integration with your workflow. Most MathML editors have a WYSIWYG
            interface so that you never have to see the MathML.</para>
        <para>After creating your content, you might run it through a conversion process, usually
            involving XSLT, to produce HTML5 and EPUB 3 output. The conversion process needs to be
            modified to include the calls to MathJax in the header. Also, the MathML will need to be
            passed through the process untouched. By default, XSLT processors will remove the MathML
            tags and only pass the CDATA through; thus, you will need to add a few lines to your
            XSLT library to make sure the MathML tags make it to the output.</para>
        <para>Finally, you may need to set up MathJax on your server. The MathJax Consortium does
            host a version of MathJax to which you can link your pages, but if you have heavy
            traffic, like to have control of the libraries used on your site, or want to customize
            MathJax at all, you will need to download and install MathJax.</para></sect1>
    <sect1 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><title>Conclusion</title><para>Recent developments in digital publishing standards are changing the way we present and
            consume information. Mathematics are a key part of this revolution with MathML's
            inclusion in HTML5 and EPUB 3. MathML brings to fruition the promise of enriched content
            for STEM industries by providing the following advantages: MathML is searchable and
            accessible, it allows easy localization of content, it is flexible in its display across
            multiple devices and in its support of stylesheets, and finally MathML's use as an
            exchange format provides endless possibilities in the way mathematical content in web
            and e-book publications can be enhanced for your audience.</para>
        <para>MathML is already supported by a number of browsers and e-readers. To fill the gaps,
            an open-source Javascript library by the name of MathJax provides MathML rendering for
            all modern browsers. MathJax is also being used to successfully add proper display of
            MathML in e-readers.</para>
        <para>The maths stack consisting of MathML, MathJax, HTML5 and EPUB 3 can be implemented by
            modifying your XML schema to include MathML, adding a MathML editor to your XML editor,
            making sure your conversion pipeline passes the MathML through untouched, and setting up
            MathJax on your server.</para></sect1>

    <bibliography xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="paper-24_References">
            <biblioentry xml:id="paper-24_mearian-2012">
                <abbrev>Mearian, 2012</abbrev>
                <author>
                    <personname>
                        <firstname>Lucas</firstname><surname>Mearian</surname>
                    </personname>
                </author>
                <pubdate>11 December 2012</pubdate>
                <title><link xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9234563/By_2020_there_will_be_5_200_GB_of_data_for_every_person_on_Earth">By 2020, there will be 5,200 GB of data for every person on Earth</link></title>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>Computerworld Inc.</publishername>
                </publisher>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="paper-24_miner-2004">
                <abbrev>Miner, 2004</abbrev>
                <author>
                    <personname>
                        <firstname>Robert</firstname><surname>Miner</surname>
                    </personname>
                </author>
                <pubdate>8 June 2004</pubdate>
                <title><link xlink:href="http://www.dessci.com/en/reference/searching/math-searching.htm">Enhancing the Searching of Mathematics</link></title>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>Design Science</publishername>
                </publisher>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="paper-24_misutka-2008">
                <abbrev>Misutka, 2008</abbrev>
                <author>
                    <personname><firstname>J.</firstname><surname>Misutka</surname></personname>
                </author>
                <copyright>
                    <year>2008</year>
                </copyright>
                <citetitle>Indexing Mathematical Content Using Full Text Search Engine</citetitle>
                <pagenums>240-244</pagenums>
                <title>WDS '08 Proceedings of Contributed Papers </title>
                <seriesvolnums>Part I</seriesvolnums>
            </biblioentry>
            <biblioentry xml:id="paper-24_fernandes-2012">
                <abbrev>Fernandes, 2012</abbrev>
                <author><personname><firstname>Rossi</firstname><surname>Fernandes</surname></personname></author>
                <pubdate>15 March 2012</pubdate>
                <title><link xlink:href="http://tech2.in.com/features/general/what-html5-means-to-you/290302">What HTML5 means to you</link></title>
                <publisher><publishername>Tech2.com India</publishername></publisher>
            </biblioentry>
    </bibliography>

</article>
